<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<spots>
    <spot><id>20230519104052</id><image>../images/TRES.jpg</image><name>Tres Reyes Island</name><location>Gasan</location><details>Tres Reyes Islands are located off the coast of Barangay Pinggan in Gasan, Marinduque. Composed of&#13;
    three islands named after the 3 wise kings Melchor, Gaspar and Baltazar, Tres Reyes Islands are popular&#13;
    island hopping destination in Marinduque. It has clear blue-green waters ideal for swimming and&#13;
    snorkeling.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot>
    
    <spot><id>20230519104642</id><image>../images/Gsasang.jpg</image><name>Gasang-gasang Festival</name><location>Gasan</location><details>Gasang-gasang Festival is a yearly colorful Easter Sunday festival in the town of Gasan, Marinduque. It is&#13;
    in celebration of the origin of the name of the town Gasan, which came from the term Gasang-gasang a type of coral that used to be seen around the town shoreline. If you're visiting Marinduque during holy week, add Gasang-gasang Festival in your itinerary.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519104951</id><image>../images/church.jpg</image><name>St. Joseph Parish Church</name><location>Gasan</location><details>The St. Joseph Parish Church of Gasan, Marinduque is located at the poblacion of Gasan, Marinduque on&#13;
    top of a hill overlooking the town. Don't miss entering the church to see the beautiful interiors with&#13;
    coconut shells adorning the altar and huge anahaw-looking decorations at the church ceiling. In front&#13;
    of the church is a view deck where you could enjoy an amazing view of the coastline and of the town.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519105234</id><image>../images/butterfly.jpg</image><name>Butterfly Farm</name><location>Gasan</location><details>Do you know that Marinduque is the butterfly capital of the Philippines? Gasan one of the six towns in Marinduque is considered as the butterfly capital of the Philippines, contributing 85% of the country’s butterfly and pupa exports. More than three-fourths of the butterfly breeders nationwide are based largely in this town and neighboring villages. Butterfly farming started only recently but is fast becoming an international growth industry with estimates of 100 million pesos worth of exports. Here's a little more information about Gasan, sometimes known also as the cultural center of Marinduque.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519105412</id><image>../images/view park.jpg</image><name>Gasan Sea View Park</name><location>Gasan</location><details>This public park is a good place to chill and relax while enjoying the cool breeze of the air. Not to be&#13;
    missed is the breathtaking sunset view where you could take your IG-worthy photos.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519105619</id><image>../images/talao cave.jpg</image><name>Talao Cave</name><location>Gasan</location><details>A maze of caverns, sinkholes, and multi-level chambers located in the interior forested part of Brgy.&#13;
    Tiguion. Can be accessed by travelling the barangay road and trekking uphill to the cave’s location.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519105835</id><image>../images/kalutang.JPG</image><name>Pangkat Kalutang</name><location>Gasan</location><details>A local band of musicians from Brgy. Bangbang playing unique pairs of instruments, sticks of wood&#13;
    (made from Kwatingan or Bayog) of different sizes struck together producing syncopated percussion&#13;
    music of local songs. Lead and organized by Maestro Tirso Serdena, an acknowledged National&#13;
    Commission for Culture and the Arts (NCCA) National Culture Bearer award. The group has performed in&#13;
    many places in the country to showcase their unique kind of music. Usually they perform welcoming&#13;
    guests and playing on birthdays and other local provincial events and holidays.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519110157</id><image>../images/boac moriones.webp</image><name>Experience Moriones Festival</name><location>Boac</location><details>Many travelers and tourists go to Marinduque for their annual Moriones Festival. Every town has their&#13;
    own Moriones Lenten Rituals, but for me the grandest is held in the capital town of Boac. If you're&#13;
    visiting during holy week, dont miss the senakulo, the processions, and the via crusis along the streets&#13;
    of Boac during Moriones Fesival.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519110424</id><image>../images/boac cathedral.jpg</image><name>Boac Cathedral</name><location>Boac</location><details>Sits on a small hill overlooking the town, the Boac Cathedral is dedicated in honor of the blessed Virgin&#13;
    of Biglang Awa. Built in 1792, it is where Filipinos and Spaniards sought refuge from pirate attacks&#13;
    during that time. Its architecture is of Filipino-Hispanic Gothic with most of the original construction&#13;
    preserved; such as the facade and main body, the belfry and the altar.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519110553</id><image>../images/museum.jpeg</image><name>Boac Museum</name><location>Boac</location><details>Located beside the Boac Town Plaza and Rizal Park is the Boac Museum. Housed in an old Spanish&#13;
    building that used to be a library and Municipal Trial Court of Boac, it is home to a collection of artifacts&#13;
    and important collections about the Island of Marinduque. Entrance fee is 20 pesos for adults and 10&#13;
    pesos for Students and Senior Citizens. The museum is open from Monday to Friday, 8:00 AM - 5:00 PM&#13;
    (with lunch break). Saturdays, Sundays and holidays are by appointment.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519110732</id><image>../images/old houses.jpg</image><name>See the Old Houses of Boac</name><location>Boac</location><details>If you love old houses like me, Boac has many of them. Although I only found one house with a National&#13;
    Historical Institute (NHI) marker declaring it a heritage house, it is still a feast to my eyes seeing a&#13;
    handful of well-preserved houses lined up on the streets of Boac.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519111002</id><image>../images/capitol.jpg</image><name>Marinduque Provincial Capitol</name><location>Boac</location><details>One of the many interesting structures in Boac is its 1927 provincial capitol building. Efforts have been&#13;
    initiated with the National Historical Institute to declare it a Historical or Heritage Site.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519111202</id><image>../images/casa real.jpg</image><name>Casa Real</name><location>Boac</location><details>Newly built replica of the old Spanish “Casa Real” that served as the administrative center of the&#13;
    province built on its original location. Today is it used by the Municipal Government of Boac as a multi-&#13;
    purpose building.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519111440</id><image>../images/kabugsukan.jpeg</image><name>Kabugsakan Falls</name><location>Boac</location><details>Located at the interior part of Brgy. Tugos, accessible from the end of the barangay road with 30&#13;
    minutes trek and river fording towards a forested area where the falls of around 40 feet is located.&#13;
    There are natural pools for swimming at its foot.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519111557</id><image>../images/battleof paye.jpg</image><name>Battle of Paye Site</name><location>Boac</location><details>Located in Sitio Paye, Brgy. Balimbing where the first successful battle of the local Marinduque&#13;
    revolutionaries led by Capt. Teofilo Roque over the American volunteers on July 31, 1900. A National&#13;
    Historical Institute marker was placed near a portion of riverbed where the skirmish happened.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519111936</id><image>../images/baliis.jpg</image><name>Baliis Sea of Clouds</name><location>Boac</location><details>Located along the highest highway system of the province that covers Brgy. Bantay and Hinapulan, the&#13;
    area offers a scenic view of “above the clouds” or “sea of clouds” experience, and can be compared or at&#13;
    par with views of Tagaytay or the Cordilleras. After the less restrictions of the Covid 19 pandemic in the&#13;
    province, lately this has appealed to almost a thousand visitors especially during the weekends. The&#13;
    Makulapnit, Bol, and Hinapulan river valleys that empties to the great Boac river are densely covered by&#13;
    low lying fog that can be observed on the early morning hours from 4AM to 8AM along the stretch&#13;
    approximately 3 -4 kilometers of this national highway.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519112108</id><image>../images/marl.webp</image><name>Marl Insect Garden</name><location>Boac</location><details>Known as the first butterfly garden in Marinduque, Marl Insect and Butterfly Garden is a great place to&#13;
    interact and to learn more about butterflies. They also have a souvenir shop selling different items made&#13;
    from butterflies.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519112332</id><image>../images/PAADJAO.jpg</image><name>Paadjao Falls</name><location>Mogpog</location><details>Located in Sitio Paadjao, Barangay Bokbok in the town of Mogpog, Paadjao Falls is an ideal place for&#13;
    picnicking and camping. To get the the falls, it requires a bit of trekking passing through dense&#13;
    vegetation. The main falls is a 15-foot high cascading waterfalls which ends in a 10-foot deep pool.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519112745</id><image>../images/slider3.jpg</image><name>Luzon Datum</name><location>Mogpog</location><details>One of the must-visits when visiting Mogpog is the Luzon Datum of 1911 marker. Located on top of&#13;
    Mataas na Bundok, you have to climb a series of concrete stairs of more 400 steps to reach the&#13;
    summit of the mountain. Here you see the Luzon Datum marker which is considered as the center of&#13;
    the Philippines. Also known as Station Balanacan, the Luzon Datum is the primary geodetic reference,&#13;
    or datum origin of all surveys in the Philippines - making Marinduque the heart the center of the&#13;
    Philippines.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519113151</id><image>../images/mogpog-marinduque-home-of-moriones-festival.png</image><name>Moriones Lenten Rites </name><location>Mogpog</location><details>The town of Mogpog started this century old masked tradition introduced by Fr. Dionsio Santiago&#13;
    around 1870 in order to encourage more town folks into the Christian faith. Men and some women don&#13;
    wooden masks and colorful costumes resembling the Roman soldiers during the time of Christ. This&#13;
    tradition is highlighted by the “Pugutan” of Longino on Easter Sunday. Today Mogpog Morions still&#13;
    practices the age old tradition of its ancient and original forms of sacrifice.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519113446</id><image>../images/Balanacan_Cove.jpg</image><name>Balanacan Cove</name><location>Mogpog</location><details>This is one of the most ideal and secluded cove of the province that witnessed the long history of&#13;
    Marinduque. This location was chosen by the Spanish Admiralty as construction and repair facility of the&#13;
    Spanish navy. The galleon “San Juan de Bautista” and almirante “San Marcos” were made in this cove.&#13;
    During the closing of WWII, on November 25, 1944, two of the four Imperial Japanese Navy warships&#13;
    camouflaging in the cove were sunk by the American dive bombers form the USS Intrepid and killing&#13;
    thousands of Japanese. Two Jap shipwrecks still lays done under 140 feet of water for advanced wreck&#13;
    divers to explore.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519113722</id><image>../images/bintakay.jpg</image><name>Bintakay Cave</name><location>Mogpog</location><details>This cave is located in the oldest limestone formation of the province, located in Brgy. Bintakay near the&#13;
    historic battle site of Camarines, a rocky protuberance where Filipino revolutionaries during the Spanish-&#13;
    Filipino war used as their last stand. This cave features wide chambers, tight squeeze passages,&#13;
    profusion of insect bats, and beautiful speleothems.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519113914</id><image>../images/tarug cave2.JPG</image><name>Tarug Cave</name><location>Mogpog</location><details>Located inside the municipal forest park, Tarug Cave can be accessed via the barangay road, the caves&#13;
    are small and don’t have deep chambers, but it offers a 300 feet tall limestone walls going to the top&#13;
    excellent for rock climbers and rappelling.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519114137</id><image>../images/Marinduque-Kangga-Festival (1).jpg</image><name>Kangga Festival</name><location>Mogpog</location><details>Celebrated annually in honor of the town’s patron St. Isidore de Labrador, patron of farmers where&#13;
    barrio folks converge at the town and parade with its own “kanga” or wooden sled pulled by a carabao&#13;
    and bedeck with different products from each locality. The celebration is capped by the contest of the&#13;
    most beautiful “kangga”, on cooking of local delicacies and the unhusking of coconuts.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519114348</id><image>../images/view deck.jpg</image><name>Balanacan View Deck</name><location>Mogpog</location><details>Balanacan View Deck and Bacud Hill- located near the boundary of Brgy. Ino, the present view deck&#13;
    which offers a 270 degree view of the northwestern portion of Mogpog, was reconstructed from a single&#13;
    storey galvanized iron roofing into a two- storey concrete slab view area.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519114604</id><image>../images/natangco island.jpg</image><name>Natangco Island</name><location>Mogpog</location><details>A protected marine sanctuary, Natangco Island is part of Barangay Silangan, Mogpog, Marinduque.&#13;
    Surrounded by 30 to 40 feet deep fringing reefs excellent for diving and snorkeling. The island can be&#13;
    reached by rented boats from Barangay Ino and Barangay Balanacan. The island boasts a strip of white&#13;
    sand beach, pristine and clear waters and rocky island formations off its coast.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519114746</id><image>../images/crocodile island.jpg</image><name>San Andres Island/Crocodile Island</name><location>Mogpog</location><details>The uninhabited island of San Andres in Silangan, Mogpog is rich in marine life below. The island is&#13;
    swim-away from the white sand coast of the village. There are numerous rock shelters and forest areas&#13;
    on the northern side of this island that is kept untapped and untouched by human settlers.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519115142</id><image>../images/church.jpg</image><name>Holy Cross Parish </name><location>Sta. Cruz</location><details>The Sta. Cruz Church is the oldest in the province, constructed in 1760, with intricately-carved retablos and pulpit still intact today. Even with renovations done in recent years, most of this historic church’s interiors and furnishings are well-preserved.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519115334</id><image>../images/BAGUMBUNGANCAVE.jpg</image><name>Bagumbungan Cave</name><location>Sta. Cruz</location><details>Bagumbungan Cave in Sitio Puti Brgy. San Isidro, Sta. Cruz Marinduque is for sure one of the best cave here in the Philippines. It is a 1.9 km. long cave and some part are still unexplored. It is protected by the Department of Environment and Natural Resources (DENR) with the help of San Isidro (Local Government Unit) to spare the cave from exploitation. According to our guide, it was discovered 7 years ago by the cave enthusiast and a tourism officer. Since then the local government has been doing so much efforts in promoting this cave as their tourist destination in San Isidro. &#13;
    &#13;
    This trip was not actually part of itinerary since the transportation in Marinduque is limited only. We can't take to miss its last trip as early as 1 pm going back to the Sta. Cruz townproper. Day 2 of our hometown vacation was beach hopping in the famous Maniwaya Island, Mongpong Island and Polo Island but due to very bad condition, we quickly changed our plan so it happened to be a caving trip in Bagumbungan.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519115545</id><image>../images/Maniwaya Island.jpg</image><name>Maniwaya Island</name><location>Sta. Cruz</location><details>Maniwaya Island is part of the town of Sta Cruz in Marinduque and is less than an hour of boat ride away from the main island. It is surprisingly undeveloped with only a handful of resorts lined along its shores of rough coral stones and white sugary sands. Its water is teeming with life although negative effects of cyanide and dynamite fishing in the past are still very much evident in one too many dead corals scattered in its ocean floor. Its rustic vibe and tranquil state are its most redeeming qualities. Plus, it is totally off the path and uncrowded so you are guaranteed to have that patch of sand to frolic under the sun with for that much needed tan</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519115758</id><image>../images/palad sand bar.jpg</image><name>Palad Sand Bar</name><location>Sta. Cruz</location><details>Travelers are not only looking for white sand and crystal water in a beautiful island, they are also searching for sandbar, a bar of sand formed in a sea or river by the action of tides or currents. One of the stunning sand bars in the Philippines is can be found near Maniwaya Island in the province  of Marinduque. It is called Palad Sandbar.&#13;
    &#13;
    Palad Sandbar is one of a kind places for outdoor enthusiasts and beach lovers. It features powdery white sands that flush through the crystal clear waters, which  appears during low tide. It's advisable to go here in the morning when the tide is usually low. You can reach sandbar via a 30-minute boat ride  from Maniwaya</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519115923</id><image>../images/ungab.webp</image><name>Ungab Rock Formation</name><location>Sta. Cruz</location><details>The Ungab Rock Formation is one of the most iconic natural landmarks of the province of Marinduque. Its most characteristic feature is the arch formed through years of erosion. Situated on the eastern coast of the island of Mongpong, the Ungab Rock Formation stands next to a beach and is surrounded by clear blue and turquois waters.&#13;
    &#13;
    Ungab Rock Formation is easily accessible through a pumpboat ride from the Buyabod Port of the municipality of Santa Cruz. It is also one of the most popular stops during island hopping activities with the Maniwaya Island as jump-off point.&#13;
    &#13;
    Island Hopping tours can be arranged with the pump boats stationed at Buyabod Port or with the resorts located at Maniwaya Island.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519120032</id><image>../images/Kawa Kawa.jpg</image><name>Kawa-Kawa Falls</name><location>Sta. Cruz</location><details>Kawa-kawa falls is located in Bangcuangan, Sta. Cruz, Marinduque. Kawa-kawa means basin because of its basin-like appearance. There are actually 2 basins, one from the top and the other at the lower part. Because there is a light rainfall before we went there, the water became a little dark but rest assured that it is clean since there are caretakers in the area and the water is flowing.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519120231</id><image>../images/MongpongIsland.JPG</image><name>Mongpong Island</name><location>Sta. Cruz</location><details>The island province of Marinduque and the first thing that comes to most people’s minds is the Moriones Festival during Holy Week. Marinduque, however, offers so much more than the colorful Lenten rites involving men and women garbed in the attire of biblical-era Roman soldiers. And so we discovered during a short trip to two of the province’s island destinations.&#13;
    &#13;
    Marinduque has intrigued us for some time now and it wasn’t because of its famed Holy Week rites. Our travel radar instead turned towards two islands off its northeastern coast: Maniwaya and Mongpong. After driving all the way to Gen. Luna town in Quezon’s Bondoc peninsula, we boarded a ferry bound for Maniwaya Island where we had booked a room at the Residencia de Palo Maria beach resort.&#13;
    &#13;
    Island-hopping was at the top of our agenda for this trip. A sunny, clear and almost cloudless day greeted us as we hopped aboard our outrigger for a 30-minute ride to another island east of our resort – Mongpong Island, sometimes called Mompong by the locals. One thing that easily stood out during our ride was the clarity of the waters around Maniwaya and Mompong. It was so clear we could easily spot colorful reef fishes underwater as our boat sped past.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519120343</id><image>../images/BathalaCave.jpg</image><name>Bathala Cave</name><location>Sta. Cruz</location><details>Bathala Caves is a complex network of caves that are said to be the playground of the Gods. Located in the rustic town of Sta. Cruz in Marinduque, the caves are believed to be mystical. According to locals, these caves are a repository of psychic power emanating from various points of the universe.&#13;
    &#13;
    Caves inside the Bathala Caves&#13;
    &#13;
    Simbahan Cave. Simbahan Cave is the biggest of the caves. It possesses a natural rock formation creating a church-like interior. The stalagmites of the cave form an altar-like structure and a silhouette of the Madonna and Child while the stalactites are bell-like in shape.&#13;
    &#13;
    Kay Coke or Python Cave. Python Cave is guarded by pythons and has a ceiling of hundreds of giant bats. The cave is deeper and darker than the Simbahan Caves.&#13;
    &#13;
    Secret Cave. The cave looks like a secret passage. Secret Cave has a unique rock formation of stalactites and stalagmites featuring impressive wall sculptures and formations at the entrance. Like the other caves, it has plenty of bats and guano.&#13;
    &#13;
    Other unnamed caves in the Bathala Caves are the cave that has an underground river and the cave that houses human bones believed to be the remains of World War II soldiers. Because Bathala Caves is a network of caves, only few have been explored so far and many caves are yet to be explored.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519120617</id><image>../images/PoctoyUnderwaterMuseum.jpg</image><name>Poctoy Underwater Museum</name><location>Torrijos</location><details>Among the well-known attractions in Marinduque is the Poctoy White Beach, a long stretch of fine white sand lined with palm trees in the coastal municipality of Torrijos. Surrounding the powdery beach are crystal clear waters that are ideal for swimming and kayaking. There are beachfront huts and cottages with chairs and tables, perfect for spending laidback afternoons on the beach.&#13;
    &#13;
    Underneath the crystalline waters is a sight to behold for scuba divers. The Poctoy Underwater Museum showcases giant Moryon monuments, which symbolize Marinduqueños iconic Moriones festival that happens every Holy Week.&#13;
    &#13;
    Aside from being one of the idyllic beaches in Marinduque, Poctoy White Beach remains to be among the emerging Torrijos Marinduque tourist spots. It attracts many local and international travelers annually because of its pristine shores and panoramic sunset views glowing over the horizon.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519120740</id><image>../images/POCTOYBEACH.jpg</image><name>Poctoy Beach</name><location>Torrijos</location><details>Poctoy White Beach is considered as the most famous beach in the mainland of Marinduque facing Sibuyan Sea. The beach features over a kilometer long stretch of pure white sand, alluring deep turquoise waters, interesting seaside rock formations, lush of green vegetation, beautiful view of Mount Malindig and looming mountains as backdrop. Visitors may enjoy swimming, snorkeling, diving and wind surfing. There are plenty of beach front resorts in the area and cottages are also available for day visitors but camping is also allowed. In spite the fact that it’s a public beach, it is clean and lively worth visiting.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519120855</id><image>../images/Torrijos Freedom Park.jpg</image><name>Torrijos Freedom Park</name><location>Torrijos</location><details>We’ve done almost half of our travel plans in Marinduque. Still euphoric from attending the Moriones Festival, still full from gorging some local food and tingling sunburn – we came back to town and felt we needed to escape and have some quiet time and just relax.&#13;
    &#13;
    With that extra time on our hands while in Torrijos,  Marinduque and craving for some space and air, we headed to the Freedom Park, which according to the welcome sign was formerly called the Luneta Park of Torrijos. &#13;
    &#13;
    It is about a few minutes walk from the town proper – impressive place where we enjoyed pleasant view of Mt. Malindig and some lazy walk. It would be nice swimming at the beach but we already visited some awesome Marinduque beaches and had enough sun so we just stayed to relax and got totally unplugged from our hectic Marinduque get-away.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519121301</id><image>../images/pulang lupa.jpg</image><name>Pulang Lupa</name><location>Torrijos</location><details>This Historical Park just outside of Torrijos town is home to the most famous battle on Marinduque during the Philippine American War.  This battle is also in the top 10 of all the battles during this period in Philippines.   Although a peaceful setting today, it was not so in September of 1900 as forces led by Maximo Abad surprised and defeated Company F of the United States 29th Volunteers led by Captain Deveraux Shields.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519121602</id><image>../images/malbog.jpg</image><name>Malbog Sulfuric Hot Spring</name><location>Buenavista</location><details>Malbog Sulfuric Hot Spring Resort or “Mabaho” is located at the foot of the mountain in Brgy. Malbog, Buenavista, Marinduque.  The hot spring has sulfur content popularly used for skin care and treatments.  Despite its rotten-egg like foul, many locals and tourists visit this place for body relaxation and healing of skin conditions. Some are even bringing home bottles of sulfuric water.&#13;
    &#13;
    </details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519121645</id><image>../images/malindig.jpg</image><name>Mt. Malindig</name><location>Buenavista</location><details>Mountains are deeply steeped into the culture of Filipinos. Pampaguenos have Mt. Arayat; Tagalogs have Mts. Banahaw and Makiling. For the residents of Marinduque, they have Mt. Malindig. In fact, Marinduque itself have been derived from “Marindik” or “Malindik”. Anthropologists may trace this cultural link to the volcanic origins of the island. Indeed, Malindig is being proposed as an inactive stratovolcano. The therapeutic, sulfuric springs of Malbog is one sign of this historical – if not prehistorical – volcanism. As for the name itself, Malindig, it is linguistically descriptive of the gentle slopes that characterize the mountain, as well the island’s high areas.&#13;
    &#13;
    Armed groups were still active until the past decade, when the military seems to have kept them in check. This paved the way for Malindig’s discovery as a mountaineering destination. Its unique location, at the heart of Southern Tagalog, creates a panorama that encompasses Mindoro, Verde Island, and Southern Luzon all the way to Bicol and Burias Island. The Tres Reyes islands are particularly enchating. Elephant Island, reportedly being developed another “Boracay”, may also be seen SW from the military radio outpost, 900 MASL. This outpost is also the staging ground to the summit assault. From this point on, you will be hiking across the forests of Malindig. Lush and mossy, they are not different from the forests in Mt. Makiling.&#13;
    &#13;
    Mountaineering groups also do what is called a “Marinduque Traverse”, involving the other mountains in the area. Notable sites to visit include the Bathala cave in Sta. Cruz, as well as several waterfalls i.e Kawa-kawa falls which is near the jumpoff to Malindig.&#13;
    &#13;
    Going to Marinduque is usually commenced by a bus ride to Lucena. From there, you can board a ferry to either Sta. Cruz or Mogpog towns. Within the island, tricycles, jeeps, and vans ply inter-town routes, but be advised that places are faraway from each other, and transpo costs are quite significant.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230519121827</id><image>../images/bellarocca_island_resort_philippines.jpg</image><name/><location>Buenavista</location><details>Bellarocca Island Resort and Spa in Marinduque is distinct from the other upscale, luxury resorts of its category anywhere in the country. All 20 hectares of Bellarocca Island Resort and Spa is mountainous terrain, with its highest point at 114 meters above sea-level. To many seasoned travellers, the images of the picturesque island of Santorini in Greece come to mind upon approaching the resort. Common to both are its rolling terrain and immaculate white buildings perched atop its cliffs: white structures that reflect the sun and contrast with the azure blue sea below. Bellarocca Island Resort and Spa is located on a small mountain island of the southern coast of Marinduque and offers 69 luxurious deluxe suites, casas, terrazas and private villas (with individual Jacuzzis and infinity pools). Guests relax in utmost privacy while enjoying the resort's complete aqua sports facilities, a full spa and wellness facility, a 9-hole golf course and other land-based recreational activities. Guests arrive on the island direct via commercial flights (SEAIR or Zest Air), private helicopters, chartered flights from Manila to Marinduque or onboard an exclusive luxury yacht.</details><date>2023-05-19</date></spot><spot><id>20230520122442</id><image>../images/20160405-162050-largejpg.jpg</image><name>Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary </name><location>Buenavista</location><details>Up next is a piece of greenery that occupies nearly 9,000 hectares of land, the Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary. It is home to several bird species such as the Zebra Dove, Serpent Eagle, Brahminy Kite, and Philippine Scops Owl. Adding to the lush green landscape are native trees such as Ipil, Narra, Yakal, and Molave.&#13;
    &#13;
    Inside the wildlife sanctuary are caves that serve as a habitat for rare species, like the cave-dwelling freshwater shrimp. Some wild animals inhabiting the protected land are the Philippine warty pig, the Philippine deer, the cloud rat, and the green racket tail. &#13;
    &#13;
    The Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary was declared as a protected land area in 2004 under Presidential Proclamation No. 696. Its forest watershed encompasses the municipalities of Boac, Gasan, Buenavista, Torrijos and Sta. Cruz. The Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary is a must-visit hiking, camping, and bird-watching spot for nature lovers and adventurous travelers.</details><date>2023-05-20</date></spot><spot><id>20230520122635</id><image>../images/Haynon Hills.jpg</image><name>Haynon Hills</name><location>Buenavista</location><details>Located at the foothills of the western side of Balagbag Mountain Range, these undulating hills that have been utilized as pasture land offers a relaxing view of scattered clamps of grassy and hilly terrain of different heights and elevation that turns color brown during summer months, due to the dry grasslands, acquiring a title of “Chocolate Hills of Haynon” but turns green during rainy season. Now is a favorite destination of hikers, mountain bikers and plain visitors. Accessible via a barangay road that turns to the left before the Malbog Sulfur Springs.</details><date>2023-05-20</date></spot>
    <spot><id>20230522095255</id><image>../images/1000.jpg</image><name>Sunset</name><location>Buenavista</location><details>Very beautiful</details><date>2023-05-22</date></spot></spots>
